Pratt, Read & Co. Collection
Ivoryton Library Association
Pratt, Read & Co. Collection
1830-2001
Comstock, Cheney & Co., Pratt, Read & Co.
2010-001
17 23 Boxes, 41 Volumes
Ivoryton Library Association
This collection contains documentation of the ivory industry, processing and trade in Ivoryton, CT during the years of operation of Comstock, Cheney & Co. and Pratt, Read & Co., successive names for the ivory factory which was the main employer in the village from the 1860's to the 1980's.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Harwood Comstock, final president of Pratt, read & Co., in 2010-2011
Biography
The Ivory processing factory in Ivoryton, CT began as S.M. Comstock Co. in 1847. With the addition of inventory George Cheney in 1862, the company became Comstock, Cheney & Co., the company that was the dominant economic and social force in the town of Essex, CT. In Deep Rive, CT, the ivory factory Pratt, Read & Co. formed in 1863. The two factories merged in 1936, retaining the name of Pratt, Read & Co. and moving the operations to the Ivoryton plant.The Falls River Flood of 1982 caused extensive damage to the factory and the ivory ban of 1989 effectively ended the factory in Ivoryton. The company had diversified into other manufacturing industries and moved the company to Bridgeport, CT before finally declaring bankruptcy and closing for good in 2010.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection includes documentation of the ivory industry, articles about ivory processing, annual reports, catalogs, shareholder reports, correspondence; correspondence related to Edith Deforest, secretary who also managed the company museum; correspondence related to Peter Comstock, president in 1930s-1980s, geneaological information about Comstock family and business correspondence, Cheney, Pratt Families, minutes, wills, mechanical drawings of machine parts produced by Cornwall & Patterson Co., small companies acquired after the piano industry began to wane, Comstock Cheney Ivoryton, corporate history, land records, invoices, financial papers, deeds, legal documents of the Pratt, Read & Company Deep River, Pratt, Read & Co. Ivoryton: articles, strike information, property records, building plans, scrapbooks, slides documenting the 1982 flood; photographs of Pratt, Read & Company Presidents; Pratt, Read & Co. annual reports (1892-1986); stock ledgers (1902-1930); the majority of the records document the history of these companies after their merger.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by topic.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Comstock, Cheney & Co.; Pratt, Read & Co.; Comstock, Samuel Merritt; DeForest, Edith M.; Ivory industry--Connecticut.; Ivory industry--Africa.; Genealogy--Connecticut.
Separated Material
1 scrapbook is located in the Oversized Local History area in the main circulation room.
- Inventory
  - Africa- articles and documents, 1942-2005 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1934-1986 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, Read Museum, Edith DeForest, 1979-2009 (Box 3)
  - Comstock, Cheney & Co., 1905-1976 (Box 4)
  - Mechanical drawings for special oreders, 1955-1993 (Box 5)
  - Mechanical drawings for special oreders, 1954-1992 (Box 6)
  - Mechanical drawings for special oreders, 1960-1993 (Box 7)
  - Peter Comstock- business correspondence, genealogical research, 1949-1983 (Box 8)
  - Pratt Read-Deeds, lawsuits, stock journals, 1839-1936 (Box 9)
  - Pratt Read - Deep River, CT, 1863-1998 (Box 10)
  - Pratt Read - Ivoryton, 1937-2001 (Box 11)
  - Slides - Falls River flood & other, 1980-1982 (Box 12)
  - Slides - Falls River flood, 1982 (Box 13)
  - Warrantee Deeds, stock transfers, 1830-1934 (Box 14)
  - scrapbooks, 1839-1961 (Box 15)
  - Scrapbook- Pratt read presidents, 1905-2010 (Box 16)
  - Histories & remembrances, 1942-1998 (Box 17)
  - From Ivory Combs to Carnegie Hall and Today by Curtiss S. Johnson, 1974 (Box 18)
  - Embossers from various Pratt Read companies, wood easter eggs from Allen-Rogers, undated (Box 19)
  - Frames b/w prints of Pratt Read factory by artist Guy Wiggins, undated (Box 20)
  - Pratt Read Museum Postcard, framed, undated (Box 21)
  - Pratt Read Museum Postcard, framed, undated (Box 22)
  - Pratt Read Museum Postcard, framed, undated (Box 23)
  - Bound annual reports, 1892-1986 (Box 23)
  - Bound stock ledgers, 1943-1956 (Box 23)
  - Stock transfer books, 1902-1931 (Box 23)
  - Supply Catalog, 1940-1941 (Box 23)
  - Cash Book, undated (Box 23)